We chase the birds, stare at the stars and measure the sky,
我々は鳥を追い　星を眺め　天を計り
just want to divine our ephemeral future.
儚い我々の行く末を占った
Now you guide wings, stay close to the etoiles and move the heaven.
今　あなたは鳥を導き　星に寄り添い　天を動かす
You shall be a precious spirit.
あなたは尊い精霊となり
As a part of world from this sandy land,
この砂地より世界を作るみなもととして
light your soul forever.
永遠にその魂を灯す
From the mud castle ship, we keep our minds on you.
泥の城船から 我々はあなたを思い続ける
Guide us, please.
我々を導きたまえ
July 2, 93 S.S.
砂刑暦93年7月2日
Benihi (Shirushi)'s funeral has been held.
ベニヒ（印）の葬儀が行われる
She was 29,
享年29
served as a teaching staff.
教育係を務めていた
We flow the dead into the sea of sand.
私たちは　死者を砂の海へ流す
Whoever sends the dead at this time must not let the tears sink.
この時　死者を送る者は　涙を流してはいけないという
Because you will be called by the souls sleeping under of the sand, they will beckon you in.
砂の底に眠るたくさんの魂に呼ばれ　早く砂に召されてしまう
That is the tale handed down.
そう　言い伝えられているんだ
Ah, you can't cry here Chakuro.
あゝ　チャクロ　泣いちゃだめだって
Don't cry,
泣いちゃだめだ
or you will be called by the dead.
死者に呼ばれてしまうよ
C'mon, clench your fingers.
さあ　指を組んで
Restrain yourself, Chakuro.
がまん　がまんだよチャクロ
Restrain, restrain.
がまんがまん
You idoit...
バカ…
Ah, I goofed again.
はあ　またやってしまった
My name is Chakuro.
私はチャクロ
I am 14 years old, male.
14歳　男性
The recording clerk of the mud whale.
「泥クジラ」の記録係である
Many times each time I see off a friendly person,
何度も親しい人を送る度に
my urge to record is increasing.
私のこの記録したい衝動は高まっていく
According to my grandfather, who was a Muin,
「無印」だった祖父のいうには
I am sickening from an illness
ハイパーグラフィア
hypergraphia
ということだった
The drifting boat on the endless sea of sand.
果てのない砂の海を漂流する私たちの漂泊船——
The population of our mud whale was 513.
「泥クジラ」の人口は513人
Our lives were together with the sand, the wind and the sunlight.
私たちの生活は砂と風と陽の光と共にあった
Concentrate!
集中して
You should get it down slow~ly!
そ～っと降ろすのよ
Get it down slow~ly!
そ～っと降ろす
Oh yeah, everyone's handy!
そうそう　みんな上手
You guys have made a lot of progresses.
ずいぶん上達したね　チビ達
Chakuro!
チャクロ
Cuz they have a good teacher!
やっぱ先生がいいからだな
Yeah.
そうだね
Everyone is better than Chakuro already!
もうみんなチャクロより上手だよ
Don't tease me!
ひどいなあ
Listen, a Shirushi shouldn't work as a recording clerk.
大体　印は記録係なんかやらないんだよ？
sentikinesis
サイミア
You are wasting your thymia!
せっかくの「情念動」を生かせないんだもん
You were appointed as a recording clerk,
記録係に任命されたのって
just cuz you're not good at thymia, right?
サイミアがヘタっぴだからでしょ？
They are even calling me the destroyer!
ヘタどころか　デストロイヤーって言われるよ
Don't tease yourself!
笑って言うこと！？
By the way,
そういえば
we were also learning thymia
俺もサミもこうやって
from Benihi in this way, right?
ベニヒにサイミアの使い方教わったんだよな
Chakuro,
チャクロ
forget about Benihi.
ベニヒのことは忘れよう？
We can't leave ourselves trapped in the death of others,
人の死にいちいち思いを寄せていたら
or we Shirushi are not able to live through.
あたし達印は穏やかに生きていけない
Yep.
そうだね
sentikinesis
サイミア
Shirushi is the name of those who can handle thymia from emotions.
「印」とは感情から「情念動」を発動させる能力者のこと
Nine in ten of the inhabitants of the mud whale are Shirushi.
泥クジラの人間の9割がそうだ
We Shirushi are all like Benihi whom we sent off yesterday.
印は昨日送ったベニヒのように
We are all short-lived.
皆短命である
Chakuro!
チャクロ
Cut some leaves of omasa bamboos from your place!
そっからオオマサゴチクの葉を切ってくれ
Since they will be used for food preservation,
食料の保存に使うから
pick 5 to 6 new leaves from as tall as possible.
できるだけ上のほうの若い葉5 6枚
Please use that!
そいつを使ってくれ
5 to 6 leaves, 5 to 6 leaves...
5 6枚　5 6枚
Chakuro!
チャクロ！
Who said you'd chop the tree!
誰が伐採しろっつったんだよ！
Stop! Don't run away Chakuro!
こら　逃げんなチャクロ！
Get back!
戻ってこい！
What the fuss?
なんの騒ぎ？
Dunno.
さあ
Hide me!
かくまって！
What have you done?
何やらかしたんだよ
Oh nothing serious.
あいや　大したことはないよ
Close the window, sand's entering.
砂が入るから閉めろ
Sorry sorry.
ごめんごめん
What's that?
それなに？
We're making your goggles.
お前らのゴーグルを作っている
For protection from the sand?
砂よけの？
You've picked up acrylic boards for us the other day, right?
この前アクリル板を拾って来たろ
Thatz for you, though it's just a prototype.
試作品だけどこれやるよ
Cool!
かっこいい！
The thick body is simply too great for me!
ゴテゴテした感じがたまんない
Decoration is a hobby of this workshop, but it's not that useful.
装飾はこの工房の趣味だから実用性はないぞ
As a return, if you find something from the sea or the islands,
代わりに海や島でなんか拾ったら
bring them right here without declaration!
申告せずに俺たちに回すよな♪
I'll show it off to Sami later.
あとでサミにも見せてやろ
Hello, chief.
首長さま こんにちは
You are wearing cool stuffs!
かっこいい物を身につけてるのね
Are you going out to the sea?
海へ出るの？
No, I am on my way to Suo.
いえ　スオウのところへ行く途中です
With your records, right?
記録を持って行くのね
Is that for the funeral of Benihi?
それはベニヒの葬儀のぶんか？
Isn't it over writing too much?
書きすぎじゃないか？
The paper is precious, use it moderately.
ほどほどにしないと　紙は貴重なんだから
I appreciate it.
いいじゃありませんか？
Chakuro's record is useful.
チャクロの記録は役に立ってますよ
It looks like a diary rather than an official record.
公式記録というよりは日記みたいね
I just can't stop writing.
書くことが止まらないんです
Maybe I'm not suit for recording clerk,
俺　記録係には向いてないと思います
but I wonder if the people who lived in our mud whale
でも　泥クジラに住んでた人が
could have written more about those happened in the past.
もっと当時のことを書き残してくれていたらって思うんです
Then why we came to live on this island?
なぜこの島に暮らすようになったのか　とか
And why our mud whale does never sink?
なぜ泥クジラは沈まないの　とか
We may understand these
もっと記録が残っていたら
if there are more records left.
俺たちはそれを理解できていたのかもって
So I write for the future.
だから俺は未来のために書くのです
Do your best!
がんばりなさい
Yes!
はい
Those who do not have the power of thymia,
首長や長老会の人などサイミアの力を持たない彼らは
are called Muin.
「無印」と呼ばれる
Most of the Shirushi die in their twenties.
二 三十代には多くがこの世に去ってしまう「印」とは違い
In the contrast, Muin are long-living.
無印の人は長命である
They live as the leaders of the mud whale.
彼らは泥クジラの指導者として生きていく
Come in.
どうぞ
Hello, Suo.
こんにちは　スオウ
Hi Chakuro.
やあ　チャクロ
I am bringing you the records.
記録　持って来ました
Thank you.
ありがとう
Did you cry the whole night last night?
昨夜はずっと泣いていた？
No... I mean...
あっいえ…　あの
I was crying too.
私も泣いていたんだ
Keep it our secret.
みんなには内緒
Benihi was a nice person.
ベニヒはいい人だった
There is no emotion recorded in your writings.
君の文章には一切　感情が書かれていない
But they are very sentimental.
それでもとても感傷的だ
Because it's a rule not to write any emotions down.
感情を文字にしてはいけない決まりなので
Chakuro,
チャクロ
I'm sorry you have to record so many painful things.
辛い記録ばかりさせてすまないね
There's nothing I can help you...
私はなにもできていない…
Why are you apologizing?
な　何で謝るんですか
Suo is doing researches on extending the lives of Shirushi.
スオウは印の人たちの寿命を延ばすための研究もしているし
And you sincerely feel sorrow for our short lives, more than anyone else.
誰よりも印の短命を嘆いています
You truly have shed more tears than me!
本当は俺なんかよりずっとたくさん涙を流してきたんです
I am stupid, writing a lot of records is the only thing I can do.
俺はバカだから大量の記録を書きなぐることしかできない
But you are clever and will have a long live!
でもあなたは賢いし長生きだ
Please solve this world's mystery
この世界の謎を解いて
and make people on this ship much much happier!
この船の人たちを今よりずっと幸せにしてください
Thank you, Chakuro.
ありがとう　チャクロ
Here, when people can not hold their emotions on their bodies,
ここの人々は感情が表に出そうとした時は
they clench their fingers in this manner
こうして指を組む
to get their feelings under control.
情動をこらえているのだ
These records will be with you even after I die.
俺が死んでもこの記録があなたと共に残って…
I hope they can help you in the future.
少しでも未来で役に立てばいい
It's an adrift island!
流れ島だ！
It's the first adrift island in the past 6 months.
半年ぶりの流れ島です
We have 5 days to go to the island for procurement.
島へ調達に行けるのは五日後あたりでしょうか
After that, it would become difficult since it will be too far.
それ以降は距離が離れて困難になる
Let's send a reconnaissance team first tomorrow.
明日まず偵察隊を向かわせよう
Then we will procure goods if it's safe.
では　その後安全ならば物資調達を
Please scout for a reconnaissance team until tomorrow, Suo.
偵察隊の人選は明日までにスオウがしてください
Do me a favor.
頼みますよ
Got it.
わかりました
The next morning we left when the sea was calm.
翌朝　波の静かなうちに私たちは出発した
Why is Chakuro here?
なんでチャクロも来てんだよ
Hope we are not go into troubles this time.
トラブルになんなきゃいいけど
It's amazing that Suo chose Sami.
スオウはよくサミを選んだよな
We all know it could be dangerous.
危険かもしれないのに
My brother trusts me.
お兄ちゃんはあたしを信頼してくれてるのよ
Go!
いっけえ！
After enter the sea,
砂の海へ出ると
you will sink in the sand if you do not use the thymia.
サイミアを使わなければ砂に飲まれて沈んでしまう
Using thymia to float the leave boat
ササ舟を浮かせ進ませるためにサイミアを使うと
consumes as much stamina as running at full speed.
全力疾走と同じほど体力を消耗する
Therefore the distance we can arrive is limited.
だからその距離は限られるのだ
Listen, never act individually.
いいか　単独行動はするな
Also, do not pick anything up since it's recce this time.
それと　今回は偵察だからなにも採ってくるなよ
Yes sir.
はあい！
Sami.
サミ
Thank you.
ありがとう
You are hot on each other!
お熱いね
Impossible!
そんなんじゃない！
Hey Sami, don't go alone!
あっサミ　単独行動はするなって
I'm fine!
いいの
But here is different from the islands I've seen.
それにしても　いつも流れてくる島とは違う気がする
It's something that people used.
人が使う物だ
I guess it's a weapon.
武器に見えるな
There were islands where we can find something people left.
今までも昔の人が使ったものが残っている島はあった
But we have never found any people.
それでも　どこにも人はいなかった
The guys in the workshop will be happy right?
工房の奴らが喜ぶよ
Sami?
ね　サミ
What?
あれ
What should I do?
どうしよう
Hey, Sami!
おーい　サミ？
What are you?
なにおまえ…
Wait!
ちょっと
Hey, I said wait!
おい　待っててば
What's this?
何だこれ？
Food?
食べ物？
Hi.
あの…
Are you OK?
大丈夫？
Tears...
涙…？
What's wrong?
どうしたの！？
Are you injured?
怪我してるの？
She was the first human I met outside of our mud whale.
彼女は　私が泥クジラの住人以外で初めて出会った「人間」だった
If we could call her a human
彼女のこの時の状態を
considering her status at that time.
「人間」といってよいのなら
But...
だが…
Stop it!
やめろーっ！
She is weakening.
この子…　力が弱って…
As I expected...
やっぱり…
She is injured.
怪我してる
She has washed her clothes.
洗濯してたのか
Hey, you'd go together?
おい　おまえまでかよ
Maybe it's her pet.
この子の連れか
Hey, where's Chakuro?
あれ　チャクロどこ行った？
I lost him on the way...
途中ではぐれちゃって…
Masoo.
マソオさん
Hey Chakuro!
コラァ　チャクロッ！
I told you not to act individually!
単独行動するなって言ったろ
And I said don't pick anything...
しかもモノ拾ってきやがっ…
She is not anything!
あの　モノじゃなくて
She is a person!
人です　人
Oh my god...
マジかよ
What should we do, captain?
どうする　隊長？
She is weakening, she may die if we leave her alone!
弱ってます　放っとくと死んじゃうかも
We interrupted the reconnaissance of the island,
私たちは　島の偵察を急きょ切り上げ
and decided to take the girl to the mud whale.
その少女を泥クジラに連れて帰ることにした
How beautiful she is.
綺麗な人…
Sami, could you put these clothes on her?
サミ　この服着せてあげてくれない？
I think they are hers.
彼女のだと思う
Yup.
うん
lykos
lykos
This scar... It seems that she get injured for quite some days.
この傷跡…　怪我してからだいぶ時間がたってるみたい
Should I tell others about I was attacted by her with her thymia?
彼女がサイミアを使って襲ってきたことは
Better not I think.
言わないほうがいいかな
It's raining.
あ　雨だ
Wow... It's a sunshower!
わあ…　晴れてるのに
It feels good!
気持ちいいね
Rainwater will be stored in the reservoir of mud whale,
雨は泥クジラの貯水池へと蓄えられ
very important for our lives.
私たちの生活の大事な糧となる
Also, it was said that rain is auspicious.
また　雨天は吉兆と言われていた
It's a rainbow!
虹まで…
Surely something good is going to happen!
きっといいことがあるね
Yeah!
うん
In our closed little world,
私たちの閉じられた小さな世界に
may this girl
この少女が
brings the future unknown to everyone.
誰もが知らない未来を連れてきてくれるのかもしれない
Everybody in our recce team is excited.
偵察隊の心ははずんでいた
For me, the first one who found her, in particular...
とりわけ最初に彼女を見つけた私にいたっては…
Ah, I can't record any emotion.
あ　感情書いちゃダメだった
What happened? Aren't you too fast?
どうした　早かったじゃないか
Emergency!
緊急事態だよ
We picked up something terribly good!
すげえもん拾った
What!
なに！？
You are supposed not to take anything back today!
今日はなにも持ち帰ってはならない決まりのはずだ
I will denounce you to the presbytery!
長老会へ申告する
Shut up, your puss-head!
うっせーなこの頭でっかち
What are you saying, you muscle idiot!
なんだとこの筋肉大馬鹿野郎が
Stop, you two!
おやめなさいな二人とも
C'mon and clench your fingers!
ほら　指を組んで
You don't wanna be internal moles, right?
「体内モグラ」になりたいんですか
Go see it with your own eyes!
てめえ　自分の目で見てみろってんだ
There's a person on that island!
あの島に人がいたんだよ
A person?
ひと？
This girl.
この子です
A per... person!?
ひ　ひと…ッ！？
Tai.. Taisha-sama!
タ　タイシャ様ああああ…！
Ah, she is awakened.
あ　気づいた
αὔρα
アウラ
An aura!
念紋が！
Will she attack us?
やる気かっ
You can't do it!
ダメだよきみっ
Here in the mud whale,
サイミアでケンカしちゃ
you can't fight with thymia or you will be punished!
泥クジラでそんなことしたら罰を受けちゃうんだよ
Release me.
はなして
She spoke...
しゃべった…
The same language...
コトバ同じだ
Seems I've been captured.
私は　捕虜…になったのね
I won't resist.
抵抗はしない
I'm the only one left.
私一人になってしまった
I surrender.
投降…します
This way, watch your step please.
こちらです　足元をお気をつけください
Thank you.
ありがとう
Aye, it's my pleasure!
あっいえ　当然なのです
Where is the girl from that island?
島の子はどうしました？
She... Chakuro and Sami have taken her to the medical office.
それが…　チャクロとサミが医務室に連れて行くっと
Oh dear.
まあ
That two brats!
あの悪ガキども！
What's your name?
君　名前は？
No.
そんなのないわ
You have one!
あるわよ
Λύκος
λύκος
Lykos, embroidered on your clothes!
あなたの服に「リコス」って刺繍してあった
Lykos, huh...
リコスかあ
Lykos, don't you shock in such an completely unknown place?
リコスは知らない場所に来ても驚かないの？
If I were you, my heart's throbbing.
俺だったら心臓バクバク
I'm curious if I were her!
あたしだったら興味津々だよ
No.
そんなのないわ
Here is the medical office?
ここは医務室？
Only young people here...
若い人ばかり
They are Shirushi.
印の人たちだよ
Their abilities of thymia and stamina decreased after the age of 30 or so.
30歳になるぐらいにはサイミアの能力も体力も落ちてきて
Some people even became bedridden.
寝たきりになる人もいる
Is it the same in your world?
君の世界でもそう？
No.
そんなのないわ
Φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Is here Fallaina?
ここは…　「ファレナ」なの…？
Fallaina?
ファレナ？
It's mud whale here.
ここは泥クジラだよ
Everyone calls here like that.
みんなそう呼んでる
Chakuro, Sami.
チャクロ　サミ
Chief.
首長さま
You have protected this girl, right?
この子保護してくれたのね？
Good job.
ご苦労様
Hello.
こんにちは
I'm the chief here, my name is Taisha.
首長のタイシャです
I wonder if you can follow me.
ついてきてもらえるのかしら
Wait a minute please, chief.
待って首長さま
Where are you going?
どこに行くんですか？
I will introduce her to the presbyters.
長老会に紹介します
But she is injured and needs medical treatment.
その前に怪我とか診てもらわないと…
You are kind.
二人とも優しいのね
But don't worry, we will take care of her.
でも大丈夫　ちゃんと気遣います
Suo, deal with the internal moles please.
スオウは「体内モグラ」のほうをお願い
Yes.
はい
Lykos...
リコス…
Brother!
お兄ちゃん！
Have you seen? She's the girl on that island!
見た？あの子があの島にいた子なのよ！
I wonder if I can be her friend!
サミ　友達になれるかなあ
It would be nice to be so.
そうだね　なれるといいね
Yup!
うん
Suo, what's wrong with the internal moles?
スオウ　「体内モグラ」がどうかしたんですか？
Since there is a rainbow, they are pardoned.
虹が出たから赦免されることが決まってね
Oni's guys?
オウニたちが？
I'm going to release them.
今から私が釈放に立ち会うんだけど
But I'm just wondering what will they do
流れ島で人が見つかったって知ったら…
if they know a person has been found on an adrift island.
何をするか
I'll go with you
俺も一緒に行きます
as a bodyguard.
ボディガードで
Let's go together!
サミも行く
No way, Sami should return to work.
ダメ　サミは仕事に戻って
Nah!
え～
I wonder whether it was caught on that island too?
もしかしてそれも島で捕まえたの？
Eh, it follow me itself.
えっ　ああ　勝手についてきて
Seems delicious.
美味しそうだね
Oh, yeah...
あ　はい
In the mud whale, those who breaks the rule
泥クジラでは決まりを破った者たちを
would be jailed in an area called the internal.
地下の「体内」と呼ばれる区域に投獄した
For some reason, thymia can not be used there.
ここでは何故かサイミアが発動しない
For us short-living Shirushi,
寿命が短い印たちにとって
it was really sad to lose our freedom and be sent into the internal.
自由を奪われる体内送りは辛い処分だった
But there were guys who repeat violating the rule
しかし　何度も規則違反を繰り返し
and get jailed times and times.
投獄される者たちがいた
Since they have spent so long in the internal,
彼らは長い時間を体内で過ごすことから
they were called the internal moles.
「体内モグラ」と呼ばれていた
It is an amnesty.
恩赦だよ
Get out.
出なさい
Ah, my body is hurt!
あ～　身体いってぇ
It's dazzling!
眩しい
We are so honored that the next chief is welcoming us in person.
次期首長さまが直々にお出迎えとは
Do not repeat absurd things.
馬鹿げたことは繰り返さないように
Treasure your limited time.
限りある時間をもっと大事になさい
Treasure?
大事？
They are the same for us.
俺たちは同じなの
It doesn't matter we are underground or on the ship.
地下も船も
In such a small world, nothing is different for us.
こんな小さい世界じゃ何をどうしたって同じだよ
You Muin have a long life.
無印のあんたらは先が長いから
You have enough time to treasure stuffs such as a mud ship.
こんな泥船でも大事かもしれないけどさ
There is something I have to tell you now.
先に伝えておきますけど…
Today, we found a person on a adrift island.
今日　流れ島で人が見つかりました
What? Really?
おい本当かよ！？
A person? Outside?
人がいたのか？「外」に！？
Do not overreact.
あまり過剰に反応しないように
Since you are still...
ただでさえあなたたちは…
After all there are worlds outside.
やっぱり外の世界はあったのか
There are worlds where people live.
人が他にもいる世界が
We can't tell it yet...
それはまだ…
We are going out.
俺たちは出ていく
As long as there is another world outside,
外に別の世界があるなら
I will leave this trivial ship behind.
こんなちっぽけな船なんか　捨ててやる
Oni!
オウニ…！
Where was that person?
その人間はどこにいた？
I can not tell you.
言えません
Don't depend on him.
そいつには頼るな
Wait us, Oni!
待ってよ　オウニ
Oni!
オウニ！
Oni is the leader of the internal moles.
オウニには体内モグラのリーダー格で
It was said that he is the top psychic of thymia in the mud whale.
サイミアの能力は泥クジラで一番だと言われていた
Indeed...
全く…
Right what I was worried...
心配したとおりだ
They may do something to Lykos!
あいつらリコスになんかするかもしれない
I am going there!
俺行きます
Chakuro!
チャクロ！
Lykos...
リコス
There is only Lykos, and the presbyters.
長老さまたちとリコスだけしかいないのか
Tell me the name of your country.
あなたの国の名前を教えて
Have you been dispatched from the home country?
君は「本国」から派遣されてきたのかね？
Home country?
「本国」？
What are they talking about?
何の話…
Please answer my question first.
先に私の質問に答えてください
Φάλαινα
φάλαινα
Is here Fallaina?
ここは…　「ファレナ」ですか？
I can not answer you.
答えられない
Unless we fully understand your purpose,
君の目的がはっきりしないのであれば
we can not reveal our identity.
我々も正体を明かすことはできないのだよ
What do they mean?
どういうこと…？
Seems presbyters understand what Lykos is saying.
長老さまたちはリコスの言うことが分かるの…？
I was forced to be brought here.
ここへ連れてこられたのは私の本意ではありません
What about your fellows on the island?
島に仲間は？
They all died.
全員死にました
I buried them.
私が埋葬したわ
Didn't you feel anything?
辛くはなかったのかね？
Such as painful...
そんな気持ちは…？
No.
そんなのないわ
απάθεια
アパトイア
She is an apatheia...
人形か…
People without emotion...
感情の無い人間だ
Oh my goodness...
何ということ
Απάθεια
アパトイア？　なにそれ？
The world is still what it was in the past.
やはり世界はまだ昔のままだったか…
It seems that there is no point in talking with you any more.
これ以上話しても意味がないようだな
Excuse me, but I have to restrain you.
悪いが君のことを拘束させてもらうよ
Lykos...
リコス…
What are you saying?
なんだよお前？
It told you to be careful upon your head!
頭の上に気をつけろってさ
Oni!
オウニ
Stop it!
やめなさい
Don't you know what will happen if you do this?
こんなことをしてどうなるかわかっているのか
I am going to see her world.
俺はこいつの世界を見に行く
You guys just play with your treasurable mud ship all your lives!
あんたらはここで一生泥船ごっこでもしてろよ…！
Lykos...
リコス…
Help, help...
誰か　誰か…
What's up?
どうしました？
It must not...
いけないよ…
If you make contact with the world,
世界に触れたら
the woes will overtake you.
災いが起こるよ
Oni escaped with that island girl!
オウニが島の少女攫って逃げやがたっ
Pursue him as soon as possible!
早く追っ手を出すぞ！
Oni,
オウニ
what are you planning to do?
どうするつもり？
I'm going to her island.
こいつの島に行く
You participated in the recce team right?
お前は偵察隊に参加したんだよな
Yep.
うん
Guide me.
案内しろ
There are plenty of things I want to write about the mud whale.
泥クジラについて私が書きたいことがたくさんある
Stacked sun-dried bricks, painted with mud, we had a toy-like castle city.
日干し煉瓦を積み重ね　泥で塗り固めたおもちゃのような塔の城に
Lots of people were living there together.
沢山の人たちが寄りすがり　生きてきたことを
I am sure you will be surprised as you are living in an extensive world.
広漠たる世界に暮らしてきたあなたがたはきっと驚くだろう
But it was the entirety of our precious world.
この島が私たちの大事な世界のすべてだった
No matter what occurs,
私は何があっても
I am going to write everything happens to us.
私たちに起こったすべてのことを
The first section
書き続けようと思っていた
乾いた海の跡　望んで
乾いた海の跡　望んで
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
まだ見ぬ対岸を描く
囚われの心のままなら
囚われの心のままなら
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
こんな傷みも知らずにいた
美しい詞を告げたひと
美しい詞を告げたひと
夜明けも待たずに
夜明けも待たずに
果てのその先を泳ぐ
果てのその先を泳ぐ
虫の唄
虫の唄
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
眠らず君と聞いた記憶
手を　ただ結んで
手を　ただ結んで
半色でも　遠い国でも
半色でも　遠い国でも
短い一章に生まれた夢を
短い一章に生まれた夢を
抱きしめに行こう
抱きしめに行こう